Amir Helali . Jarvis Consulting

Skilled and solution-driven full-stack developer with more than a year of experience. My critical thinking approach, application of software engineering principles, and adherence to testing, has allowed me to consistently create and deliver highly optimized, well-structured solutions. Java, .Net, REST APIs, RDBMS/SQL, React and Angular are my forte with a competency in Azure cloud services. My personal and professional experiences have made me highly adaptable and have taught me excellent communication and time management skills; therefore, I thrive in collaborative environments or working independently under pressure. I am dedicated to continuously improve by learning new concepts and technologies and eager to showcase my abilities.

Skills

Proficient: Java, Net, React, RDBMS/SQL, Linux/Bash, REST API, Docker, JUnit, NUnit, Agile/Scrum, Git/Github

Competent: Angular, Python, Azure, JavaScript, NodeJS, Spring, Powershell, C++, Google Cloud Platform

Familiar: Kubernetes, Xamarin, TensorFlow, Microsoft Power Platform, Figma

Jarvis Projects

Project source code: https://github.com/jarviscanada/jarvis_data_eng_AmirHelali

Cluster Monitor [GitHub]: Developed a linux cluster monitoring agent to collect and store important hardware specifications and resource usage data for each node. This solution enables administrators to make key decisions based on the collected data for resource management and planning. It was Developed using Feature Branch Workflow within Git to ensure encapsulation and tracking. Implemented bash scripts to automate data collection and storage. Setup PostgreSQL database as a docker container to ensure compatability and data integrity. Configured a cron job to automate the execution of scripts for consistent data collection and storage.

Highlighted Projects

Travel Companion: Developed a social media style web app for travellers to meet up with other fellow travellers and keep track of their activities during their adventures. Used Agile methodology to ensure sustainable development. Designed wireframes and mockups using Figma to provide a blueprint for the visual elements. Implemented a modern UI for profiles using React, CSS and Bootstrap to ensure responsiveness, consistency and maintainability. Created ERDs using Visual Paradigm for database design. Implemented APIs and middlewares using Node.js and Express to process data exchange between the client and the server. Implemented a Google maps functionality using the Google maps api. Built a CI/CD workflow using Github actions. This was a group capstone project during my studies which allowed me to master and showcase my skills as a full-stack developer, and gain experience in project management while collaborating with others.

Firewall Rules API: Transformed Powershell scripts in charge of creation, configuration and storage of firewall rules, into serverless REST APIs, using Azure Functions and .Net. The purpose of this project was for improved integration, scalability and maintainability. Implemented authentication using Azure AD to ensure security. Utilized various Azure App-Service APIs to perform CRUD operations. Utilized Entity Framework ORM for improved productivity, and Nunit for testing. This was my main project during my co-op term at MPBSD and it allowed me to hone my skills as a backend developer in a real work environment and to learn about fundamental Azure cloud concepts. During this project, I gained real experience with Agile Methodology by participating in sprint plannings, daily scrums, sprint review and retrospective.

Professional Experiences

Developer, Jarvis (2024-present): Participated in daily scrum meetings to ensure work items were on track without any issues. Developed a program for Linux cluster management following Agile principles, and utilizing Docker, bash scripts, PostgreSQL, Git/Github, and Cron.

Developer(Co-op), Ministry of Public and Business Service Delivery (Jan 2023-Aug 2023): Participated in sprint planning, daily scrum, sprint retrospective, and presented my work in sprint review to get feedback from the clients. Transformed more than 5000 lines of Powershell scripts in charge of firewall rules to serverless REST APIs using Azure Functions and .Net. Optimized SQL queries using stored procedures, views, and triggers. Updated and maintained an internal charity web application's backend and frontend based on business needs using React and .Net. Collaborated on a client application's front-end to be AODA compliant using Angular.

Education

Seneca College (2019-2023), Honours Bachelor of Technology - Software Development, Software Design and Data Science - 4x annual Scholarship - 3x President's Honours List - GPA: 3.9/4.0

Miscellaneous

- Winner of the 4th annual Microsoft & OPS hackathon in the best increases efficiency, effectiveness, and speed of government operations category
- $\bullet~$ CPR & First-Aid certified
- Making video games in Unity & Unreal during my off time
- Snowboarding
- Soccer Player(goalkeeper)
- Classical Guitar Player
- Fan of Fantasy and Sci-fi books, movies, shows, and video games
- Traveling and learning about new cultures through their people, landmarks, and cuisines